[Music]
Welcome to this Business Central launch
edition 2025 release wave 2 session on
purchasing analytics.
According to a recent IDC study when
they asked SMB customers both in the
small and medium segment um about things
that have impacted their business the
last 12 months 31% of customers stated
that supply chain disruptions have
impacted their business. So we thought
that might be a good place where we
wanted to improve analytics to make sure
that you can at least analyze risks to
supply chain um and maybe plan ahead.
So with the updated PowerBI app for
purchasing, we are trying to help you as
a procurement manager to uh forecast
future uh procurement needs. Um analyze
your supplier quality. We'll come back
to what that means. Uh and also dive
into supply chain risk. Some examples
here could be simple single item
suppliers, parto analysis of suppliers
like what's your supplier
uh composition uh when you think about
what you buy. I'll come back to that. Uh
and for instance geography
um and also uh for the PowerBI app um a
new page where you can use AI to analyze
your purchasing data. Apart from the
visual part, we are also open sourcing
the everything uh all the code for the
PowerBI app for purchasing.
So let's uh let's dive into PowerBI and
see a number of different ways you can
you can analyze
your risk within your supply chain.
The first place where you can look into
risk is directly on the front page of
the purchasing PowerBI app. The
purchases overview.
Here we have an updated purchase
quantity by location
where all the purchase documents are
present. So posted purchase invoices but
also return orders. And this is shown
across different warehouses. So imagine
that you have a lot of return orders in
a particular location. That means that
something is going on in that warehouse
that you need to return so many goods.
So that could be a sign of like a
qualities uh issue with the way they
handle things in the warehouse or it
could be that the particular vendors
delivering to the west warehouse is is
have suboptimal quality of the things
you buy. Another analysis where you can
maybe dive deeper into this is your
purchases by item. This is an updated
report in this app as well and it has
two new um visuals. One is this one
where you can see like a flow of your
purchases by fiscal year and by item
category and you could maybe use this to
get an overall idea of trends. We'll
come back to more that about that in the
forecasting section.
Another thing is uh down here where you
can see kind of by item category and you
can filter this down to a particular
item or list of items. You can you can
see how much do we purchase in local
currency compared to how many we buy and
that will give you kind of an idea of
your let's say financial exposure and
maybe also with the quantity part maybe
your like inventory exposure if you have
a lot of items or a lot of money bound
or in a particular type of of item.
Next is the purchases by vendor. Uh this
one got two new visuals. The first one
here is a what's called a parto
analysis.
So down here I have a slicer where I can
where I can I can say uh in this
particular 80% so 80% of the value I buy
across all vendors is supplied by vendor
1, two and three. that means that my
like risk exposure
is uh might be quite high because if any
one of these three vendors have issues I
might have issues right so so that is a
way to see your exposure across the
vendors on on risk if they can't deliver
if they if there is a I don't know if
maybe geographical risk let's say that
you had we had an issue like last year
where there was some problems in the US
canal where a a ship a cargo ship was
kind of blocking that. So by seeing the
purchase amounts by vendor um I could
easily get that world map and maybe if
there's a crisis I can kind of see from
where in the world my vendors are
located. Especially if you have a lot of
different vendors, maybe you can
immediately see a pattern here on this
visual uh on the map.
Okay. Next is purchases by purchaser. So
now we are talking about the actual
procurement uh agents or officers. Uh
you can see here Lena uh Jim Benjamin
blank is uh we don't have that data but
uh you could imagine that um either this
visual or the purchase value by
purchaser this completely new report to
this uh page uh here you see purchase
quantity and amount so for instance I
can see that blank let's say that it
this was Jim that gym is kind Maybe
maybe there's a single purchaser risk in
this company because we have some people
working in procurement and then we have
Jim. So what happens if either Jim is
committing fraud or maybe Jim um has
like too big of a load on in the
purchasing department and if Jim is
going on vacation or like I don't know
is run over by a truck what happens like
in this case maybe you should spread the
risk across multiple people working in
procurement. So that's also a a way to
look at risk. Okay. What else? Purchases
by location. So and this is vendor
location again. But also here you see
your risk exposure to different uh
warehouses. Let's say that you you have
a dis maybe it's fine but maybe a
disproportionate
amount of purchasings going to one
warehouse. uh maybe it's fine but maybe
that warehouse is now a bottleneck for
your operations. Um and you can you can
do that across all purchases but again
of course you can filter this to a
particular group of things or or items
um uh or or a vendor as well. So
everything that you can filter on in the
report um is then showing you the risk
by that particular dimension.
Another new report purchase returns
overview. I mean it's nice that like now
we have a new report showing an some
overview of a type of document. Okay,
completeness but this is actually a
place where you can also identify risk
because this is the kind of the the
whatever you buy and return and for
whatever reason is risk, right? you can
see whether you uh with the return
reason codes of uh damages or defects or
warranty uh you can you can look into
the quality of whatever you are buying
um and uh and maybe look at I don't know
uh defects and then defects uh you you
can find out both in in this case it's
actually fabricum incorporated that is
the sole um kind
source of defects. Okay. So maybe
there's a quality issue with Fabricam
and especially with the item 10,0002.
So both uh both that but also um you can
also see kind of your financial exposure
to return reasons uh what's the credit
amount by uh by this in this particular
case. uh even though you have defects,
the defects are amounting to $1,000,
right? So maybe it's fine. Um but if
what if you had credit amount uh out
there for like a million that that's
basically something maybe you paid for,
it doesn't work, you need to return it,
but you still have that uh the the
credit part the vendor owes you that. So
there's also like financial risk uh to
the quality. So quality is both fin risk
for against your customers but also risk
financial risk uh of things that your
vendors uh owe you. For completeness we
did create our new report here as well
for purchase quote overview. Um maybe
this uh the the example I could think of
when I saw this uh could be that maybe
you had like a fraud risk if what if you
had Helina having like 10 times as many
purchase quotes as their peers. Maybe
there's something Helina is doing that
is maybe it's fine. Helena is doing most
of the work but maybe there's also some
patterns there where abnormal uh quote
behavior by a single purchasing uh
person.
The next report also new is a symmetry
for what we did for sales last semester.
These are key purchase influencers. Uh
in in the spring we did key sales
influencers. It's a this is a AIdriven
report. Um
actually it is 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 10
times to this is 20 reports in one in a
sense for each types of documents. We
can ask the question what influences the
document number to be a purchase per
posted purchase receipt and then you get
some AI insights. This is just
statistics. It's just dividing the
domain of of these uh entries for for
this particular type of document. Uh
either um when something happens then
you have a whatever 4.8
eight time higher likelihood of that.
And then there's also a segmentation
part of of this that states that um when
uh when spend reliance is lesser than
one whatever it is like maybe my demo
data is horrible here. uh but you have
two different AI generated reports uh
the things that are influencing
something to happen and a segmentation
of the of the space and that is so these
are two reports times the different 10
10 different documents is potentially 20
different reports in this one
uh then we'll let me just do the
purchase forecast the last one vendor
quality analysis This is uh also related
to risk. So this is a new report. This
is one of my also one of my favorite new
reports in the release. Uh here you have
the single supplier risk on different
items. So number of vendors out here,
the things you buy up here and then uh
each type of item category up here. So
for instance here I can see that within
my miscellaneous category I have three
vendors that can supply the Atlanta
whiteboard. Fine. Uh I if I do that I
can kind of zoom into those and I can
see uh my exposure. But uh imagine that
this was and this is by the way um one
of the things where we buy 272,000
currencies of that. Right. So there's a
big bubble here. So imagine a world
where this was not three vendors but the
big bubbles were actually in the one
category here. Those with only one
vendors mean that you are like you have
to make sure that that particular one
vendor can supply or can deliver, right?
And that means any any items any things
on this axis here is at risk if that one
vendor have a problem. It could be that
they have have a problem in their supply
chain chain like towards their suppliers
or it could be a logistics problem. It
doesn't really matter if if that vendor
cannot deliver you have a problem for
all the products on that line.
Yeah. And then the final uh part of this
demo is the the forecasting on
purchases. Uh this is purchasing
forecasting on just amounts. But uh but
of course here you want to likely to um
to forecast either I mean here I can
forecast what is likely to be uh bought
by Lena or I can forecast what are the
like what is the financial like what
money do we need to set aside to buy
furniture or uh anything you can again
uh filter to as with the other if you
seen some of the other PowerBI sessions
in this um launch edition. The
forecasting here is a classical
data mining or machine learning. It is
AI but it is old school AI.
It's a statistical model that just use
the window of transactions from the past
here to predict the future. And uh we
have chosen I think 3 months of the
future to be predicted. We have chosen
to show up or lower bounds. You can and
we have probably taken a choice of the
seasonality of of these purchases. If
you are in a business with like buying
Christmas
uh ornaments, then you are in a
different seasonality than a business
that is uh like a supermarket that's or
whatever it is, right? So seasonal I
mean supermarkets have seasonality but
the the things that are bought bought
like every day, every week, every month
is different than a business that sells
on a quarterly or yearly basis where you
have peaks in your so you can change
those seasonality settings and
everything related to the forecast
visual here by editing the the report
and and kind of change the parameters to
fit your need. That's something that uh
that that you need to do.
Yeah. So that's uh what I wanted to show
you from uh PowerBI. A lot of insights
related to risk uh you still need to
kind of make changes based on this. So
BI cannot help you with that. But
hopefully a lot of the things from the
IDC
um
review with that supply chain risk is a
real thing. um you now have some tools
to at least know where you are exposed
and then you can proactively
uh plan so that you your exposure is
reduced
though I know it was a lot to consume.
We have four new report pages, four
updated pages in the purchasing app.
Purchasing app was the one thing that
got the most love in this release wave
in analytics. So when you go and update
or install the app, go look for these
changes and then think about some of
these scenarios um I talked about and
see how you can help uh your business
reduce your risk.
If you want to learn more, um there's a
PowerBI
um
landing page for purchasing analytics
and that landing page you can reach to
from aka.ms/bc
purchasing analytics. In there, I showed
in the screenshot here a navigation
directly to the PowerBI part where all
our investments for this release wave
came in. And you can read all about
different personas, different scenarios
and and and report like documentation
article for each page in the PowerBI
app. That's it for purchasing analytics
in this video, but just uh stay tuned.
If you don't know our LinkedIn channel,
we definitely want to invite you in on
aka.ms/bc
LinkedIn. This uh is a LinkedIn uh
profile from the product group of
Business Central. You should follow that
to get weekly news updates on things
around the product. And you're watching
this on YouTube. This is hosted on our
YouTube channel aka.ms/bc
YouTube. Not only do we talk about uh
what's new here, but we also have
co-pilot and AI videos, tips and tricks,
technical deep dives, and even um under
the hood, which is a series of like
videos that are coming prior to a
release, even before uh features really
get to the release plan, kind of what's
coming. So, uh, you should definitely,
um, bookmark the the YouTube channel.
For partners, the aka.ms/bcall
aka link is gathering every AKA
resources that you probably need to
know. So, go check that out or bookmark
it. And if you are a business central um
yam sorry if you are a Microsoft partner
for business central and not on our
yammer network yet you're missing out on
a lot of interesting and fun discussions
and important discussions and questions.
So aka.ms/bcy
yammer go there and make sure that you
are part of the network. um because if
you're not uh your
uh other other partners out there is is
just have an advantage. Uh finally for
both for customers and for partners our
office hours happen um typically once a
month 45 to 60 minutes presentations and
discussions on all things business
central going forward like new
initiatives whatever um that aka link
aka.ms/bc
office hours is giving you the schedule
for the next ones. Uh so we hope to see
you in the upcoming office hours whether
you are a customer or a partner. And
with that this is it. I hope you have a
great day and I hope that you go and
make your procurement department much
more datadriven with a new PowerBI app.
Thank you.